Alright, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is עין, Ayin, however
due to תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and whatever, we are picking up
on the top of ס״ט עמוד ב׳. Samach Tet Amud Bet. We
are dealing with a discussion about whether the position of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer as explained by רב Rav is that the שבעה נקיים
Shivat Nekiyim can all be counted not only just the first and
the seventh day and not only just the first, but even the
seventh at the very end. And based on that, we're trying to
challenge it or prove it from various discussions about these cases where
a woman goes to the מקוה Mikvah multiple times because of טבילה
בזמנה. Tevilah Bizmanah. So let's pick up from the top of ס״ט
עמוד ב׳, Samach Tet Amud Bet,
and it says it's talking about a woman who came before us
and basically she said that she bled, but she doesn't know how
many days she bled and she doesn't know when she bled and
whatever. So basically if she comes in the daytime, then she goes
seven nights and eight days because maybe she's ending נדה, Niddah, so
starting tonight is maybe tonight is the end of her seven nights,
and maybe she's a זבה, Zavah, and then today might be the
last of her seven days, but then maybe she might have seen
a second ago before she came to us at night, which means
she'll need seven days other than today, which means eight more days
and then all the days in between. So seven nights and eight
days, which the point of this is to prove the fact that
she's going in the morning now the day she shows for a
זבה Zavah proves that even without having counted the seven days that
would be enough, which proves like רב's Rav version of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that she could just actually count the last day and
that would be fine, the day she's right now here. But now
we're going to finish it. So it says like this: אתיא לקמן
ברילוותא, Atei L'Kaman B'Rilusa, she comes in front of us in the
evening, יהבינן לה תמני לנדה ושבע לזיבה. Yahavinan Lah Tami L'Niddah V'Sheva
L'Zivah. So eight for נדה Niddah and seven for זבה. Zavah. So
seven for זבה Zavah the גמרא Gemara is going to challenge right
away. Why is that any different? You know, she needs to come
this morning and the next eight days for the reason that we
have said, meaning this morning might be the last of the seven
days, but she might have seen a second ago before she came
to us at night, which means she'll need seven days other than
today, which means eight more days and then all the days in
between. So we're going to correct that. We're going to say זבה
Zavah also means eight days. The question is why eight for נדה?
Niddah? And the reason of eight for נדה Niddah is because she's
coming to us tonight. So let's say, I don't know, it's Sunday
night. So maybe tonight is- so maybe Sunday night is the last
of seven nights, you know, is the last- she saw the last
on seven days from Sunday through שבת Shabbos and no, that wouldn't
work,
from Monday through Sunday she saw and now she's going to go
to the מקוה Mikvah Sunday night. So she'll go now Sunday night
she came to us. Okay, that's at one extreme. On the other
hand, maybe she just saw today, so a second before she arrived
in front of us. So if she saw a second before she
arrived, that's so Sunday night is effectively Monday, right? So Monday, Tuesday,
Wednesday, Thursday, Friday, שבת, Shabbos, Sunday, and then she'll go to the
מקוה Mikvah
again on Sunday night. So she's going from
one Sunday night and the next Sunday night and all the nights
in between, because you can do the math, interpolate that's eight nights.
Okay. So basically because she came to us at night, it gives
us one more night for the- going to go to the מקוה
Mikvah that night. So that's how it comes to eight nights for
נדה. Niddah. Okay, seven for זבה Zavah doesn't make sense, we're going
to correct it. So גמרא Gemara says: זיבה תמני בעי, Ziva Tami
Ba'i, זיבה Ziva still needs eight. אלא איידי דאיירי שבע לנדה ותמני
לזיבה, Ela Aidei D'Airi Sheva L'Niddah V'Tami L'Ziva, fine, they're both the
same, both seven for נדה Niddah and eight for זיבה. Ziva. So
גמרא Gemara isn't happy with that answer either. בליליא תמני בעי לנדה,
B'Leilya Tami Ba'i L'Niddah, like we just explained, if she's coming at
night then it would be eight for נדה. Niddah. So the גמרא
Gemara says: זיבה דפסיקא ליה לא שנא כי אתיא קמן ביממא ולא
שנא כי אתיא קמן בליליא חשיב לה. Ziva Depsika Lei Lo Shna
Ki Atia Kamman B'Yimama V'Lo Shna Ki Atia Kamman B'Leilya Chashivlah.
So זבה, Zavah, it's always going to be eight days of
זבה. Zavah. Okay, eight days of זבה. Zavah. נדה דלא פסיקא ליה,
Niddah D'Lo Psika Lei, נדה Niddah is not always the same thing,
thank you, דכי אתיא קמן בליליא בעי תמני, D'Ki Atia Kamman B'Leilsa
Ba'i Tami, if you come to us at night it's eight nights
of נדה, Niddah, ביממא לא בעי תמני, B'Yimama Lo Ba'i Tami,
if it comes in the day it's not eight nights, it's only
seven nights of נדה, Niddah, לא חשיב לה, Lo Chashivlah, it's not
bothering to mention the fact that it's also
a different- it says so it's very strange, because the fact that
the ברייתא Baraita itself distinguishes and it says- I see it's not
actually the ברייתא. Baraita. Yeah, see, it's not really the
ברייתא. Baraita. The ברייתא Baraita says if she comes in front of
us today 15. So the גמרא's Gemara real question into this is
really a גמרא Gemara figuring out night versus day, it's not the
ברייתא. Baraita. So the ברייתא Baraita says 15. So the גמרא Gemara
says let's figure this out, she comes today, I got 15, that's
seven plus eight. If she comes at night however, then it should
be eight plus eight, eight for נדה Niddah and eight for זבה.
Zavah. So the גמרא Gemara says, "Alright, you're right, really sometimes 15,
sometimes 16, but we said 15 because it's always 15." That's not
so bad, now that we came to the text because the discussion
of night and day was the גמרא's Gemara discussion. So the גמרא
Gemara is saying fine, yes, sometimes it'll be 16, but we're saying
15. Alright, anyway that proves that at least going to that ברייתא
Baraita that you don't need to count the prior days because you
can count, you know, just at the very end. So doesn't that
prove to be like רב'ס Rav's version of רבי אליעזר? Rebbe Eliezer?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. אלא לאו שמע מינה, Ella lav shema mina,
so he says the גמרא Gemara says like this. אי סלקא דעתך
ספורים לפנינו בעינן, Ei salka da'atach sefurim lefaneinu bainan, if you need
to count the days to come in front of me meaning you
have to count them as they're coming, כולהו הני טבילות למה לי?
Kulhu hani tvilot lama li? Why do you have all these טבילות
tvilot for a זבה? zava? תשפור שבע והדר תטבול. Tishpor sheva vehadar
titbol. Go seven and then go to the מקוה. mikvah. You definitely
don't have to go to the זבה zava now because you haven't
counted the days before. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait, wait, what's
this question? I mean, she shows up in front of us and
we say, oh you might be ending your seven זבה zava days
today. Go today. You might be ending them tomorrow. Go tomorrow. But
the גמרא Gemara says what what do you mean you might be
ending them? You didn't have you didn't do your counting. So this
proves you don't need to count and that it's enough that you
that the last day you see your טהרה tahara and this proves
רב'ס Rav's version of רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. Wait, wait. I understand
למה תשפור שבע והדר תטבול lama tishpor sheva vehadar titbol so don't
count,
why does it say count, what's how do you? אי סלקא דעתך
ספורים לפנינו בעינן. Ei salka da'atach sefurim lefaneinu bainan. ספורים לפנינו בעינן
Sefurim lefaneinu bainan is the claim that you need to start the
counting at the beginning and count all the days as they come
in front of you. So if you think that that's a requirement,
there's no logic why she should be going to the מקוה mikvah
all these times, right? Because
she's definitely not טהורה tehora now. So you see that it's the
רבנן. Rabbanan. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה, Amar lei, so
that's a good proof, that's like רב'ס Rav's version of רבי אליעזר.
Rebbe Eliezer. So אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב יוסף לרב אשי.
Amar lei Rav Acha breih deRav Yosef leRav Ashi. So רב אחא
בריה דרב יוסף Rav Acha breih deRav Yosef said to רב אשי,
Rav Ashi, לאו כדמתרצינן לה. Lav kematartzinan lah.
One minute, you've already sort of like fudged the ברייתא Braita a
little. You've already said it's really sometimes 16 but it says 15.
So you're really already saying it's not perfectly accurate anyway. And not
only that, more than more importantly than that, because that you could
just say 15 is always 15, is that the ברייתא Braita actually
said the woman came in front of us and said I haven't
bled at all. And then you reinterpreted that to mean I bled
and I have no idea how much I bled. Right? If you
remember that from yesterday, the original version of the ברייתא Braita was
she said she didn't bleed at all. And you didn't bleed at
all, why you going to the מקוה? mikvah? So we completely reinterpreted
it anyway. Once we're reinterpreting it,
תרצה הכי, Tirtza hachi, interpret it this
way. ספרתי ואיני יודעת כמה ספרתי. Safarti ve'eini yoda'at kama safarti. You
know what? I bled, I don't know how many days I bled,
I counted, maybe. I think I don't know how many days I
counted, maybe I did count, maybe I didn't count. איבעית נידה ספרתי
איבעית זיבה ספרתי. Iba'it niddah safarti iba'it zivah safarti. Maybe I counted
what was a נידה, niddah, it wasn't really required, maybe I counted
as a זבה. zava. So basically, you're saying, oh look, she didn't
count. Well, if she doesn't know about anything, maybe she also doesn't
know whether she counted or not and how much she counted. And
in that case, מטבילין אותה ט' טבילות. matbilin otah tesha tvilot. ספרתי
ואיני יודעת כמה ספרתי. Safarti ve'eini yoda'at kama safarti. So the גמרא
Gemara says, wait one minute. If she says at least she counted
but she doesn't know how many days, חד יומא מיהא אי אפשר
דלא ספרה. Chad yoma meiha ee efshar d'la safra. So at least
she's claiming she counted one day. So at least she's already one
day into the process, right? Why are we assuming she might not
have begun the process at all? חסרה לה טבילה. Chasra lah tvila.
One less טבילה tvila בזיבה beziva because maybe she's already she's at
least counted one day. אלא אוקי, Ella oki, she doesn't know that
either. אימא איני יודעת אם ספרתי אם לא ספרתי. Eima eini yoda'at
im safarti im lo safarti. All right, so we completely reread that
ברייתא. Braita. But anyway, not completely, but anyway. The point being that
there are definitely some indications that a זבה zava does not need
to count from the get-go and from the beginning of the seven
clean days. Only at the end she knows she's clean, she does
a בדיקה bedika and she's fine, she goes to the מקוה mikvah
as opposed to positions in the משנה Mishna like רבי עקיבא Rebbe
Akiva that said every day has to be counted, רבי יהושע Rebbe
Yehoshua that said you can only use the days you counted, maybe
you can have gaps but you can only use them. And even
a version of רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer beginning and end still needed
you to frame it from beginning and end. רב Rav is the
most lenient that you don't have to do the whole process, it's
enough to mark it at the end and you're fine. And as
I told you yesterday there's major discussions about, you know, what is
the לכתחילה lechatchila בדיעבד bedi'avad requirements of doing the שבעה נקיים. shiva
neki'im. The שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch rules like a lot of ראשונים
Rishonim that read that the whole משנה Mishna says if a woman
counted only one and seven, which means לכתחילה lechatchila she's supposed to
count all seven. Not all everybody agrees with that but that's the
way the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch rules. And then he's willing to
say at the first stage and which is really the large position
of the overwhelming position of the ראשונים, Rishonim, whether it's one and
seven, whether it's one or seven or even if it's a middle
day, רב Rav with the as I told you yesterday the approach
of the ראב"ד Raavad that you don't even need a beginning or
an end point to frame it, really any day is fine. He
says that's fine. But then he says, but there is an opinion
which is the ספר התרומה Sefer HaTruma according to רבי חנינא, Rebbe
Chanina, you דוקא davka need one and seven ואין להקל. ve'ein lehakel.
And then that raises important questions about, you know, how absolute the
ואין להקל ve'ein lehakel is in real שעת הדחק sha'at hadchak and
someone to interpret anyway that even when he says one and seven
it doesn't literally have to be the end points, it could really
be any two times even if it's not the end points. So
there's a whole very important question about a woman forgets doing her
בדיקות bedikos and so on, what is the minimum amount that would
make it that would make it acceptable. One other thing I will
say also which is interest about the idea of ספורים לפנינו. sefurim
lefaneinu. You saw as we had pointed out yesterday, the logic here
of requiring for example every single day, it's hard to see what
that logic would be if it's just to prove that she's טהורה.
tehora. Right, normally the logic is she checks she's טהורה, tehora, she's
not bleeding, you can assume that that continues it's a חזקה chazaka
and so on. Why would you need every single day? We said
well that's the idea of that the וספרה לה שבעת ימים, vesafra
lah shivat yamim, שבעה נקיים shiva neki'im means that there's an act
of counting, and maybe every day has to be marked, and that
could easily be the position of רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. Given that,
there's an interesting discussion in the אחרונים, Achronim, although again, we'll look
at ראב''ד, Ra'avad, so that's quite... we look like
רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, how much he goes like that. There's an
interesting discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim about, about,
I'm sorry, in the פוסקים. Poskim. Number one, there's a question about
like should she do a ברכה? Bracha? We do a ברכה Bracha
before ספירת העומר, Sefiras HaOmer, so maybe she should do a ברכה.
Bracha. So that gets discussed. Of course, it gets ruled out because
we've never found that anywhere, but that's an interesting question. Why not?
Maybe because it'll have to get up, it'll maybe she bleeds, it'll
stop and have to start again. Anyway, that's interesting whether you actually
consider that like a מצוה Mitzvah by itself or just a process
of getting to a stage of being able to be טהור, Tahor,
but not really an independent מצוה. Mitzvah. More interestingly, there are some
אחרונים Achronim that think, that it's not in the גמרא Gemara anywhere,
but some אחרונים Achronim that think that, well I'll say it both
for קולא Kula and חומרא. Chumra. Some want to say that the
whole reason she checks, why does she have to check? She did
הפסק טהרה, Hefsek Taharah, she knows she's טהור. Tahor. So there's a
fascinating position, so we substitute a זבה, Zava, we substitute as a
formal reason, but there's a position of I
believe either חתם סופר Chasam Sofer or נודע ביהודה Noda Biyehudah and
he uses this לקולא L'Kula about a woman who has who's bleeding
and has a מכה Maka and she can never get a clean
בדיקה. Bedikah. So it's one thing to say you can sort of
attribute it to the מכה Maka and say that it's not uterine
bleeding. But during this שבעה נקיים, Shiva Nekiyim, it's not enough to
say it's not a problem. You have to actively see you're not
bleeding. You understand the difference? If you just attribute it to the
מכה, Maka, it's no different than not having done a check. How
do you deal with the requirement that you have to actively do
a check if you have a מכה Maka and you're constantly bleeding?
So he actually claims that maybe the whole point of doing the
בדיקה Bedikah is to consciously mark the days. And therefore he says
that maybe in these extreme cases there could be some type of
a substitute that if a woman is very sort of conscious and
focuses and feels that she senses that she's not having uterine bleeding
even without doing the actual physical בדיקה, Bedikah, that that might be
able to count because maybe this is just a way of marking
the days because we already can assume that she's not having her
menstrual bleeding. So that's like a fascinating opinion לקולא L'Kula in very
extreme cases used by the חתם סופר. Chasam Sofer. Some אחרונים Achronim
take a similar approach לחומרא L'Chumra and they say, it very much
gets to this גמרא Gemara we just did here. Let's say a
woman maybe she does the first check that she needs to, but
then she sort of in the middle she sort of forgets, she
forgets she's in the middle of counting שבעה נקיים Shiva Nekiyim and
then she remembers towards the end of the week. Or a more
common case is a woman did a check and saw she thought
it was no good, she thought she was טמא. Tamei. She said
that's it, forget it, after I have to go start all over,
whatever, I'm a נדה Niddah again, blah blah. And then days later
she shows it to the Rabbi, the Rabbi looks at it and
says it's actually not a problem. So the question is does the
lack of consciousness that you're during the שבעה נקיים? Shiva Nekiyim? Right
here he's using the concept of the conscious awareness. So once he
said maybe that's all you need, that was
one לקולא. L'Kula. Is it a criteria? Is this idea of וספרה
לה V'Safrah Lah an idea of sort of being consciously aware? Now
that seems to be exactly what the גמרא Gemara is saying is
no, right? That you, a woman could show up on day seven
not even aware and you don't need ספירה לפנינו, Sefirah L'Faneinu, but
if you say you need a one and seven, which is the
other opinion, then maybe you certainly need this conscious awareness. So there
are some אחרונים Achronim that make this claim that a woman it's
not enough that she does the right בדיקות Bedikas if in the
middle somehow she thought she was no longer in her שבעה נקיים
Shiva Nekiyim that that could be a problem. Okay, so that's interesting
issues that come out of, again, none of that's explicit in this
גמרא, Gemara, but it gets to the heart of what is the
point of the counting of the שבעה נקיים. Shiva Nekiyim. Let's look
inside the פשט Peshat of the פסוק. Pasuk. It says וספרה לה
שבעה ימים אחר טהרה, V'Safrah Lah Shiva Yamim Achar Taharah, so you
need לכתחילה L'Chatchila to count. How can you say you don't need
לכתחילה L'Chatchila to count? No, what does וספרה לה V'Safrah Lah mean?
The question is וספרה לה V'Safrah Lah might just mean wait until
seven days. I mean, or count means is count that seven days
have passed since the last time I bled. It doesn't mean that
there's this מצוה, Mitzvah, this act of counting. Count seven days, okay,
one minute, it's been the last time I bled was Sunday, Monday,
Tuesday, fine, go, it's been seven days, you can go to the
מקוה. Mikvah. No, it means you have to know they're נקיים Nekiyim
though. What? I have to know they're נקיים. Nekiyim. Right, and you
know they're נקיים Nekiyim because you didn't see any blood. It doesn't
mean there was an active act of checking. Okay, so with that
we end the discussion of the counting of doing הפסק טהרה Hefsek
Taharah and שבעה נקיים Shiva Nekiyim and pretty much from here to
the end of the מסכת, Masechet, we have like three דף, Daf,
or if you count ס', Samech, more than three, but after ס',
Samech, three דף Daf which are like probably the most dense part
of
practical הלכות נדה. Hilchos Niddah. And then at כתמים, Kesamim, those two
combined are 90 percent of הלכות נדה, Hilchos Niddah, and now until
the end of the מסכת, Masechet, it's really more back to more
general טומאה Tumah and טהרה. Taharah. Let's take a look now at
the משנה. Mishnah. הזב והזבה והנדה והיולדת והמצורע. HaZav V'HaZavah V'HaNiddah V'HaYoledet
V'HaMetzora. So you have a זב, Zav, a male זב, Zav, a
זבה, Zavah, and a נדה, Niddah, and a יולדת, Yoledet, a woman
who gives childbirth, and a מצורע. Metzora.
All of these share the common trait that they make that the
idea of like, well, of משכב ומושב Mishkav U'Moshav and things that
they sit on. So let's take a look. Why does he say
זב Zav and זבה, Zavah, not מצורע Metzora and מצורעה? Metzorah? Good
question. Okay, שמעתא, Shmesa, because we've been talking so much about זבה
Zavah you want to make the explicit... They share the common trait
that they make that the idea of like of משכב *mishkav* and
מושב *moshav* of things that they sit on. So let's take a
look. Why do they say זב zav, *zav* and זבה zavah *zava*,
not מצורע metzora *metzora* מצורעת *metzorat*? Good question. Okay, שמיסו *shemeisu* because
we've been talking so much about זבה *zava* you want to make
it explicitly bring in the man. שמיסו *shemeisu*, they're טמא tamei *tamei*,
מטמאין במשא עד שימקה הבשר *metamein be'masa ad she'yimakeh habasar*.
They are טמא tamei, *tamei* if you carry them until their flesh
basically decomposes, right. Because now of course the point is, and the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to ask, of course they're טמא tamei
*tamei*, they're a מת met *meis*. Right? As a dead body, you're
טמא tameh במשא *tamei be'masa*. So we'll take a look at what
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* explains. It means that there's an aspect of
טומאת מושב *tumas moshav* that still applies with them, okay, even even
when they're dead until the flesh decomposes. עכו"ם שמת טהור tahor? מן
הטמא *Akum she'meis tahor min hatamei*. Now if a non-Jew dies, remember
non-Jews are considered טמא tameh *tamei* when they're alive as a זב
zav *zav* and other types of things and so on. Now even
a non-Jew when he's dead is טמא *tamei*, but the general assumption,
there's a מחלוקת *machlokes* in of the תנאים Tannaim. *Tannaim*, but we
generally assume that he does not cause טומאה tumah באוהל *tuma be'ohel*,
which is by the way questions about like, you know,
a כהן kohen *Kohen* going into a hospital, or going into medical
school. So medical school is a problem because you have to touch
the corpse, right? Once you're a doctor, you can handle it because
it costs nothing. The problem is training for it and you're not
yet a doctor. But the question also is just going under the
same roof. Now I have some nephews that are כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*
that are so strict about the opinion that even a non-Jew causes
טומאה tumah באוהל *tuma be'ohel* and they won't go in, for example,
to the Metropolitan Museum because of the mummies.
So we generally rule that non-Jews are not מטמא באוהל *metamei be'ohel*,
don't cause טומאה tumah *tuma* if you're under the same roof, but
they do cause טומאה tumah. *tuma* by touch. Yes, what do you
want to say? I know a כהן kohen *Kohen* who got a
פסאק *psak* to go to medical school by getting his roommate from
YU to do all the cutting for the anatomy. Who allowed that?
I don't think I should say. No, not the פוסק *posek* who
allowed that. Which medical school allowed that? Einstein? Really? Oh my god!
I'm stunned! Oh my god! Okay fine, moving on.
Einstein. Anyway fine. Okay, I'm not going to get into them. Anyway,
so but here we're talking again from the perspective not of a
corpse but for... still worry.
There you go. We're talking here not from the perspective of a
corpse, which a non-Jew is מטמא *metamei*, but from the perspective of
a non-Jew who's considered to be like a זב *zav* and the
special טומאה tumah *tuma* of a זב *zav* in terms of משכב
*mishkav* and מושב *moshav*. So that would not apply once he dies
even before the flesh decomposes, because his whole status as a זב
*zav* was rabbinic. בית שמאי אומרים כל הנשים מתות נידות *Beis Shammai
omrim kol hanashim meisos nidos*. All women when they die, die as
נידות *nidos*, meaning relevant to the previous הלכה halacha *halacha*. If a
נידה *nida* dies or a זב *zav* dies or a זבה *zava*
dies, there's still some טומאה tumah. *tuma* that relates to משכב *mishkav*
and מושב *moshav*. Well, בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* says when women die,
they they basically bleed at the moment of dying, so we have
to assume all women are נידות *nidos* for this הלכה *halacha* that
there's still some טומאה tumah, *tuma* of משכב *mishkav* and מושב *moshav*.
בית הלל אומרים אין נידה אלא Ela, שמתה נידה *Beis Hillel omrim
ein nida ela she'meisa nida*. Excuse me, if unless she knows she
was a נידה *nida* before she died, you don't assume she became
a נידה *nida* in the act of death.
Yes, what? Doesn't the same thing happen like if a man was
a, you know, a man doesn't have the same thing like a...?
You don't understand? Well, I assume people... would people die...? No, no,
no. He's not saying that. People... no, because because again, when people
die, like, don't the bodies usually like their bowels empty and... no,
that's not true? Not unless they're beheaded. If they're beheaded, they definitely
do. Really? Anyway, I'm assuming the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is extrapolating from
the fact that in death sometimes there's an evacuating of a... of
like of liquids and whatever. And uterine blood?
Well, that's what I mean that it's extrapolating. Okay, so בית הלל
*Beis Hillel* says no, that's not true, you don't have to worry
about that. I'm sorry, but what do we need to convey in
additional טומאה tumah? *tuma* for somebody who's dead? Well, that's the question
in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. The point is that even though a
corpse all these all these people have טומאה tumah *tuma*, are טמא
*tamei*, but there's a tiny little extra thing that applies to them
because as a זב *zav*, זבה *zava*, נידה *nida*, etc., there was
a certain טומאה tumah *tuma* that applied to things that they sat
on that was unique to them and not not apply to corpses.
And we're going to continue that status for a certain while after
they die. Okay, so let's see let's see the discussion in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. I don't understand why they're saying the womb would
be a נידה *nida*, but the man wouldn't be a זב *zav*
when he died. I don't know, whatever they thought about the biology.
Also because blood flow from a woman happens more, you know,
when a man I assume... well, that's actually that's טומאת בעל קרי
*tumas ba'al keri*, it's not about a זב *zav*. A בעל קרי
*ba'al keri* is more like it's a spurt, but זב *zav* is
an unusual case. נידה *nida* is natural and it happens without it
sort of coming out with a spurt, so maybe they assumed that.
Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. מאי במשא *Mai
be'masa*? What does it mean that they cause טומאה tumah, *tuma* when
you carry them? אילימא במשא ממש *Eilima be'masa mamash*? Literally you're carrying
them? אטו כל מת met, לא מטמא במשא *Atu kol meis lo
metamei be'masa*? I mean a corpse causes טומאה tumah במשא *tuma be'masa*.
What's special about these? Why do they need to specify? They're a
corpse anyway. אלא Ela, מאי במשא באבן מסמא *Ela mai be'masa be'even
mesama*. You might remember אבן מסמא even mesama *even mesama* came up
once before. It means you've got a huge boulder. Now basically halachically
if you sit on a נידה *nida* or a זב *zav* or
a זבה *zava* or whatever sits on a seat, even like twenty
seats down, it's still considered their משכב ומושב mishkav u-moshav, *mishkav u'moshav*
and it's an אב av. הטומאה *av hatuma*. Okay, now the thing
is though that would also apply to a corpse because... far than
anything directly down would be in their sort of essentially, you know,
the same way the טומאה tumah. goes up and down by a
corpse, it would also cause it that way. So that but anyway,
but the case about let's say it's a stone that
that the when you're sitting on it did not exert any sort
of weight on the thing underneath it. So you'd have a huge
boulder on top of like a cushion and somebody sat on the
boulder. So that would not actually make the thing underneath a משכב
או מושב mishkav o moshav because there's actually no weight, you know,
that's being additional or there is but it's infinitesimal, and therefore but
it still is this status called אבן מסמא even mesama. which the
thing underneath becomes a ראשון rishon not an אב. av Okay, so
that is so let's take a look.
ואבן מסמא ve-even mesama דכתיב de-ketiv והייתית אבן חדא ושומת על פום
גובא. ve-haitit even chada ve-sumat al pum guva. There was one stone
it was placed on the opening of a hole. So מאי טעמא?
mai taama? So anyway so the point is there's still a little
bit of טומאה tumah, left from this is all rabbinic from the
fact that when they were alive they had טומאת משכב ומושב. tumat
mishkav u-moshav. So even when they're dead, they have a little bit
of that טומאה tumah? left that things that are underneath them or
whatever still are considered a ראשון rishon not an אב until the
flesh until the flesh dissolves. Wait, if they were put on an
אבן מסמא. even mesama, And the thing underneath it. Right, so basically
the corpse is sat up on a stone. Right,
exactly. What? The case is the corpse is sitting on a... Well,
it's a little bit unclear. It says... it might be that if
they sit on a משכב ומושב, mishkav u-moshav yeah if a corpse
is lying on some type of a seat, maybe it means that
we give it the טומאה of אבן מסמא, we treat it like
a ראשון. rishon. You know, or it might mean yes exactly this
case, it's on a boulder and then even the thing underneath the
boulder is treated like a ראשון. rishon. Okay, so it's anyway it's
this very limited still remnant of טומאה. מאי טעמא? mai taama? What's
the reason? אמר רבא amar Rava גזירה שמא יתעלפה. gezeirah shema yitalfa.
We're concerned that they might faint, that it looks like they're dead
and they're not dead. So therefore we want to extend a little
bit of this טומאה if they might still be alive this might
be they might still cause טומאה. So why not just apply it
by all things? Right, you know. So anyway, תני משמיה דרבי אליעזר
tani mishmei de-Rabbi Eliezer אמרו עד שיבקע כריסו. amru ad she-yibaka keriso.
So he's not satisfied that or he doesn't maybe it's an earlier
point I don't know what they think anyway that is that the
flesh decomposes. He says it goes until the stomach actually bursts open.
I don't know why we assume that that happens. So anyway, the
point here what I think is more interesting than this, which is
more relevant למעשה, le-maaseh, is the awareness that we could think somebody's
dead and they might only have fainted. And that becomes very interesting
in the halachic literature about determining the moment of death, particularly in
the 19th century when it became this big fear that in the
larger secular world that people would be buried alive.
Edgar Allan Poe, thank you, was like scared to death that he
was going to be buried alive. As Michael pointed out when I
gave this שיעור shiur on שבועות, Shavuot, they used to have a
thing where they would put in the graves a like a rope
to pull and a bell on top. So if you woke up
buried alive, you could pull the rope and people would know you
were still alive. And so anyway I was not aware, Michael pointed
out, that that's where you get the phrase dead ringer from.
Anyway, so that was a real question about how much is Halacha
concerned that we might be diagnosing somebody as dead and they're not
dead. So this גמרא Gemara actually is brought into that discussion where
the גמרא Gemara says look, we might think they're dead and they're
not, they might only have been fainted. And therefore what is טמא
is a ראשון rishon because of that? Yeah, so bizarre, it's some
very limited rabbinic טומאה, yeah, I don't know why exactly that way
but yeah, I chose... Anything? No? Okay. Let's move on. Otherwise there'd
be no טומאה? What? Otherwise there'd be no טומאה on the cushion?
Well, if he actually had only fainted, then there would be no
טומאה regardless as a מת or this. But the point is that
from the very get-go, we're going to treat this person not only
as a corpse, but even as a possible still alive נדה, niddah,
זב, זבה or whatever. How does that help a person who fainted?
It doesn't. No. I'm applying it for the more relevant question of
diagnosing death and when do we start burying the guy. But what
it says, it says, what's the reason behind the משנה Mishnah? זו?
zu?
Right. Because he might have fainted. Which means that what will happen
is, is that he'll wake up and he'll say, 'Oh wow, like
oh great you weren't טמא, now we can all go home and
we're fine.' And then we won't... and then we what will not
have made the things that he was on טמא even though he
was a זב or even though she was a נדה. niddah. So
we have to sort of do this somehow to... it's a little
unclear because if he does wake up and he was has fainted
then it's not enough for this טומאה, it's משכב ומושב and it's
the whole thing. So it's not exactly clear but presumably, you know,
it'll keep us aware of the fact that he might not be
dead and it seems to be that that's a... again maybe it'll
even help that we won't bury him too quickly, I don't know.
But at least
it keeps us aware. which is part of that whole literature. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, so anyway, so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* goes on. אלו דברים שמת *Elu dvorim shemeis*. תניא *Tanya*,
אמר רבי *Amar Rebbi*: מפני מה אמרו Amru, דברים שמת טמא מטמא
במשא *Mipnei ma amru dvorim shemeis tamei mitamei bamasa*? Why did they
not apply this טומאה *tuma* to a dead non-Jew since a non-Jew
when he was alive was also treated like a זב *zav*? לפי
שאין טומאתו מחיים מדברי תורה Torah, מדברי סופרים *Lefi she'ein tumaso michayim
mideivrei Torah mideivrei sofrim*, anyway, the whole טומאה *tuma* when he was
alive as a זב *zav* was rabbinic, so when he's dead we
don't have to extend that טומאה *tuma* a little bit of why
that maybe he's still not dead and maybe he's still alive and
so on, that's going a little overboard. Okay, so that's the end
with that משנה *mishna* which as I said was a little bizarre
but also in some ways very relevant to the question about diagnosing
death and how quickly we make that ascertainment. Now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* has a nice little digression. Now let's take a look. תנו
רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*: שנים עשר דברים שאלו אנשי אלכסנדריא את רבי יהושע
בן חנניה *Shneim asar devarim sha'alu anshei Aleksandria et Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Chananya* or חנניה *Chananya*. So 12 things the people of Alexandria asked
רבי יהושע בן חנניה *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya*. We'll see how it
ties in in a minute. Presumably these people were Jewish, as we'll
see from the nature of the questions. It's not one of these
classic, you know, disputations with the non-Jewish skeptic or philosophers or whatever,
these seem to be sincere questions, but they are Alexandria which was
a pretty Hellenized Jewish city. So anyway, here's what they asked him.
ג' דברי חכמה *Gimmel divrei chochma*, ג' דברי אגדה agada. *Gimmel divrei
aggada*, three aspects of wisdom which really mean הלכה *halacha*, three אגדית
*aggadic* discussions, ג' דברי בור *Gimmel divrei bor*, three foolish questions, and
ג' דברי דרך ארץ *Gimmel divrei derech eretz*, and three questions about
like, it says 12, י"ב *yud-bet*, 12.
Okay, and three questions about like about basically, you know, how to
make a פרנסה *parnassa* or ways of being in the world. So
let's take a look. ג' דברי חכמה *Gimmel divrei chochma*, here was
the three areas of wisdom, meaning הלכה *halacha*. הזב והזבה והנדה והיולדת
והמצורע שמת ועד מתי מטמאים במשא *Hazav vehazava vehanida vehayoledes vehametzora shemeis
ad masai mitamin bemassa*. So they asked him this question: should they
continue to have this טומאה *tuma* of משכב ומושב *mishkav umoshav* or
some related form of it even after they're dead? אמר להן amar
lahen, עד שימוק הבשר *Amar lahen ad she'imok habasar*. Well, he says,
yeah, you're right, it should be, maybe they're just fainted, maybe they're
not really dead. So we have to extend this additional טומאה *tuma*
and it's until the מיתה *meisa*, until the flesh decomposes. Okay, that's
our משנה *mishna*, that's how it's a tie-in. בת משולחת מה היא
hi, לכהן *Bas meshulachas ma hi l'kohen*? So here's a good interesting
question. A man divorces his wife and it says that he cannot
remarry her after she has been with another man. Okay, so so
the question is let's say he violates that and he does remarry
her. What status would the child of that have? Because normally we're
familiar with the idea that a child of an עריות *arayos* that's
forbidden by כרת *kares* or worse is a ממזר mamzer, *mamzer*. A
child of a forbidden relationship that is forbidden to a כהן kohen.
*kohen* even if it's just by a לאו *lav*, a negative prohibition
like a כהן גדול kohen gadol, *kohen gadol* and an אלמנה almanah
*almana* or a כהן kohen *kohen* and a גרושה grushah *gerusha* or,
you know, whatever, would make a, would make the child would be
a חללה chalala, *challala*, would not be permitted to marry a כהן
kohen *kohen*. But that's because it is the product of a forbidden
relationship of a relationship that's specifically forbidden to כהנים kohanim. *kohanim*. Here
you have something that's neither ממזר mamzer *mamzer* because it's not כרת
*kares*, and it's not specific to כהנים kohanim *kohanim*. Is the offspring
of this relationship somehow forbidden similar to like the חללה chalala *challala*
and forbidden to כהנים kohanim *kohanim* or not? So בת משולחת *bas
meshulachas*, the phrase of משולחת *meshulachas* is that he cannot after he
sent her
away he can no longer now remarry her. So the phrase in
the תורה Torah, *Torah* is that he sent her away. And now
he took her back in violation. That daughter, מה היא לכהן *ma
hi l'kohen*? What's her status to a כהן kohen. *kohen*? מי אמרינן
קל וחומר *Mi amrinan kal vachomer*? Maybe we should say a קל
וחומר *kal vachomer*. ומה אלמנה לכהן גדול שאין איסורן שוה בכל *Uma
almana l'kohen gadol she'ein issuran shaveh bakol*, when it comes to an
אלמנה *almana* and a כהן גדול kohen gadol, *kohen gadol* that that's
not a universal prohibition, first of all it doesn't even apply to
other כהנים kohanim *kohanim* and it certainly doesn't apply to non-כהנים kohanim
*kohanim*. Okay, so בנה פגום *bna pogum*, the child is is not
valid to marry other כהנים kohanim. *kohanim*, that's a חלל *challal* because
it was a product of a forbidden
sexual relationship with a כהן kohen *kohen*. So זו שאיסורה שוה בכל
*zu she'issura shaveh bakol*, this that it's a universal prohibition of remarrying,
a man remarrying a woman his wife after she has been married
to another man, אינו דין שבנה פגום *eino din shebna pogum*, how
much more so, it's a broader prohibition, how much more should the
child be prohibited? או דלמא *O dilma*, or do you say no,
מה לאלמנה לכהן גדול שהיא עצמה מתחללת mitchalelet. *ma l'almana l'kohen gadol
shehi atzma mischaleles*, when is the part of the interest in logic
of the way the children of these forbidden כהן kohen *kohen* prohibitions
become forbidden is because the logic is is that the כהן kohen,
*kohen* has sex with let's say a אלמנה *almana*, and she becomes
she also becomes a חללה chalala, *challala* because she was a partner
in this forbidden sexual act. She also becomes for כהנים kohanim. *kohanim*
specifically, she becomes a חללה chalala *challala*. Now even if he dies,
so now she would still be an אלמנה *almana*, she in theory
could have married another כהן *kohen*, she's not a גרושה grushah *gerusha*,
right? But she can no longer marry another כהן *kohen* because this
act with the כהן *kohen* made her a חללה *challala* because she
was engaged in this forbidden act. And because she becomes a חללה
*challala*... her child also becomes a חלל. Now if רבקה Rivkah were
here, she would of course point out, so the kids, that it's
only the woman who's involved in the forbidden act that becomes a
חללה, the man, the כהן never becomes forbidden, right? His כהן status
never changes from engaging in these acts, it's only the woman with
which he has sex whose status changes, which is very true and
yes it certainly. And so if you're a divorced woman and you
marry a כהן. Yeah.
The children are not כהנים kohanim, essentially. Nothing happens to him. He's
still so he can do all the כהן things. While he's married
to you, no, because as sort of as a social sort of
strategy to get him to divorce and so on because he's actively
transgressing, but it does not affect his personal status. If he divorces
this divorced woman or she dies or whatever, then he goes. If
he divorces if he gets rid of this woman that he should
not have married then he's fine. Right, for him. For him, right.
But she once she's engaged now the גרושה case she was forbidden
even before she married him, but let's say you take a case
of this case, an אלמנה and a כהן גדול, where nothing, where
otherwise she could have married other כהנים. kohanim, Now that she engaged
with this forbidden act with this כהן גדול, specifically about a כהונה
kehunah prohibition, then her she becomes a חללה and forbidden to other
כהנים kohanim as well. It sounds like there wasn't there's no problem
really for a כהן to take this kind of a woman, it's
only a problem for the woman? No, no, that's not the point.
It is a problem that he's prohibited and he would get lashes
and the whole thing. But the point is that when we talk
about acts stigmatizing people, they stigmatize the women that כהנים can marry.
The forbidden types of sex never stigmatize the כהנים themselves who are
engaged in the act. That's the issue.
Okay. So maybe we should say that since she herself becomes a
חללה, that that's why it goes down to passes down to her
kid. But here, the status of this woman does not have a
personal status change. So therefore, maybe it should not apply somehow to
the child, which is another way of also saying that maybe since
this is not a prohibition that relates to כהנים and the child
isn't a ממזר, maybe the status doesn't apply to the child as
well. So the גמרא Gemara, says, אמר להן, היא תועבה. hi toeva.
It says by the פסוק pasuk about a man remarrying the wife
he divorced who married another man, that that is a תועבה, toeva,
that is an abomination. So היא, she is, ואין בניה תועבים, ve-ein
baneha toevim, not her children, תועבים. toevim. It only applies she her
children do not have any status that applies to them. Now you
have this huge תוספות Tosafot that says, I don't get it. Why
how do we take it for granted that that she doesn't become
forbidden? Maybe she should also become forbidden to a כהן. You know
how do you sort of know these things? And again, he brings
in the fact which is the obvious backdrop. Well no to him,
but not to כהנים. So she's not מתחללת. Okay, she never becomes
her into כהנים. So the obvious other point here is is that,
as I said, it's not a כהן prohibition. So the idea that
the offspring become forbidden in a non ממזר case or the woman
becomes forbidden is when it's a uniquely כהן prohibition. And since this
isn't the case, neither she nor the offspring, which is sort of
the backdrop of all of this, which is what some of these
תוספות Tosafot seem to discuss. And he's also not forbidden to her
from a subsequent
union? No,
well, that would depend. If you would say that she would become
a חללה then even from a subsequent union. If here the גמרא
Gemara is contemplating the possibility that her status is unchanged but the
offspring are no good, then the גמרא Gemara then only from that
union. But that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara rejects. Since her status,
you know, basically, well it doesn't say this explicitly, actually it does
say her status is תועבה, toeva, but anyway, but part of what's
going on here is she's never forbidden to כהנים, so therefore the
children also do not become forbidden to כהנים, which was the way
the גמרא Gemara sort of set up the question to begin with.
Okay. She's forbidden to her first husband. Her first husband, forbidden to
a כהן, right, exactly. Now if she divorces. Well she is, because
she's a גרושה actually, but okay.
But not for this. For remarrying. So she but it says תועבה
היא, toeva hi, היא תועבה. hi toeva. So if she divorces that
first husband she shouldn't have remarried, does her status go back to
being a normal. Yeah, yeah, it's only vis-a-vis him, right. Okay. Alright,
so that's number so that's question number two. Question number three, it's
fascinating like why of all things these three questions. Anyway, שני מצורעים
שנתערבו קרבנותיהם זה בזה. shnei metzoraim shenitarvu korbanoteihem zeh bazeh. What? They
were saving them up. They were saving them up, right. I mean
that it's also fascinating that it's the people of Alexandria. These are
very obscure questions, you know, the fact that they were so really,
yeah. Well there aren't that many things listed as תועבה toeva in
the תורה, and here we are four pages from the end of
ש"ס Shas and we finally ask this question. Right. First time in
ש"ס. Shas. It's true.
Okay. שני מצורעים שנתערבו קרבנותיהם זה בזה. shnei metzoraim shenitarvu korbanoteihem zeh
bazeh. Okay, now you have two מצורעים metzoraim that whose קרבנות korbanot
got mixed up with one another. Now a מצורע metzora does not
get out of being a מצורע metzora until he brings his קרבנות.
korbanot. Now if they were both alive and their קרבנות korbanot were
both alive, no problem, you bring both קרבנות korbanot and you say
whoever this belongs to, that's whose קרבן korban it is. But the
first קרבן korban of one. What can you do for the
second for
the for the
guy who is still alive for the מצורע metzora. who is still
alive? We say, well, bring the second קרבן. korban. No, because maybe
this guy's קרבן korban was already brought and this second קרבן korban
is like a חטאת שמת בעליה, chatas shemeisu ba'aleha, you can't bring
it. Okay, don't bring the second קרבן. korban. But maybe it's his
and now he'll never stop being a מצורע. metzora. Okay, so what's
he going to do? Oh, so give a קרבן korban with a
נדבה. nedavah. You can't give a חטאת chatas with a נדבה. nedavah.
So he's stuck, right? He can't bring the קרבן, korban, if you
don't bring the קרבן korban he can't get out of being a
מצורע. metzora What are you going to do? Okay, so אמר להם,
amar lahem, so basically it was a setup to get to a
case where you have a מצורע metzora who had a ספק safek
having brought his קרבנות. korbanos. What are his options? Okay, how will
he ever get out of this? They could say the same thing,
right? Like he forgot whether he brought it or not. Yeah, but
this is more interesting. Exactly. אמר להם, amar lahem, he said to
them, כותבין נכסיכם לאחרים, kosvin nichseichem leachairim, put all your property in
your wife's name or somebody, write over all your property to someone
else, okay, so you're poor. How does that help? והוי עני, vehavei
ani, now that you're poor ומביא חטאת העוף הבאה על הספק, umeivi
chatas ha'of haba'ah al hasafek, because a מצורע metzora who's poor, his
קרבן, korban, his חטאת chatas is not an animal חטאת, chatas, it's
a like a mammal it's a bird, and we have a special
הלכה that although you can never bring a חטאת chatas on a
ספק, safek, but if it's a bird חטאת chatas you're allowed to
bring it even though you're not sure you're obligated, which goes into
a lot of what we actually did learn in this מסכת maseches
about women who are not sure, you know, how many cases of
childbirth and so on, that a קרבן korban of יולדת yoledes can
be a חטאת העוף, chatas ha'of, and you can bring a חטאת
העוף על הספק. chatas ha'of al hasafek. You bring a bird חטאת
chatas even if you're not sure you're obligated or not. So he
said fine, that's applied for a מצורע metzora when he's poor, make
yourself poor and do that. So now the גמרא, Gemara what, even
though the
the other guy's חטאת? chatas? Oh, it's also. So the גמרא Gemara
has a version of that question. So let's see what the גמרא's
Gemara question is. So now the גמרא, Gemara that's the quote of
this ברייתא, beraisa, now the גמרא gemara as you see they switch
into Hebrew. The גמרא Gemara now discusses why that's a legitimate answer.
So the גמרא Gemara says, והאיכא אשם, veha'ika asham, wait a minute,
the גמרא Gemara says, but a מצורע metzora doesn't have to just
bring a חטאת, chatas, he also has to bring an אשם, asham,
and an אשם asham is what you do with all, you use
all the blood to put on the ear and his toe and
his finger and the whole thing, and that's part of the טהרה
taharah process, and that's an animal, that's not a bird, so you
have the same problem, you can't bring an אשם asham on a
ספק. safek. So what are you going to do with it? So
אמר שמואל amar Shmuel כשקרב אשמו, keshekarav ashamo, oh, he had brought
his אשם asham beforehand, so all he's left with now is the
חטאת. chatas. So אמר רב ששת, amar Rav Sheshes, so רב ששת
Rav Sheshes says, גברא רבא כשמואל לימא הכי gavra raba kishmuel leima
hachi unquote? A great person like שמואל Shmuel could say such an
answer? כמאן, keman, who you going like? אי כרבי יהודה דאמר אשם
קבע, ei kerabi yehudah de'amar asham kava, so there we're going to
find out, similar to those questions, that it's not because if you
have designated an animal, but there is a certain stage where your
status as rich or poor is determined and for the קרבנות. korbanos.
Okay, at what stage are you defined to be rich or poor?
We said that right now he has, you know, sort of made
himself poor. Okay, but that means like but but maybe his status
has already been fixed as rich. Okay, when is that determined? So
there's a debate, there are three opinions. One is when you do
the bird thing, which was a week before you bring the קרבן,
korban, you know, they dip the birds in the blood and you
send them free. One was when you bring the חטאת chatas and
one was when you bring the אשם. asham. So if you say
that it's not fixed till you bring the חטאת, chatas, then you
have some latitude to move here. You already brought your אשם, asham,
there's a question whose חטאת chatas was brought, and now you can
make yourself, you know, poor and bring go ahead and bring this
חטאת. chatas. But if it was established from the time you brought
your אשם, asham, okay, then it's too late. What are you going
to do? So the גמרא Gemara, says,
so who is he going like? אי כרבי יהודה דאמר אשם קבע,
ei kerabi yehudah de'amar asham kava, if it's like רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehudah, there's a debate which we'll quote that says that the אשם
asham fixes your status of rich or poor. וכיון דקבע ליה אשם
בעשירות, vecheivan dekava lei asham ba'ashirus, since he's already brought his אשם
asham before you did this trick, לא מצי מייתי חטאת דלות, lo
matzi maisei chatas dalus, you can't bring your חטאת chatas as a
poor person. דתנן, detnan, and here we're going to see when your
status is fixed. מצורע שהביא קרבן עני והעשיר, metzora sheheivi korban ani
vehe'ashir, a מצורע brings a קרבן korban for a poor person and
then he becomes rich. או עשיר והעני, o ashir veha'ani, or a
rich person and then he was rich and he became poor.
At which stage is his status fixed? So if he brought some
of the קרבנות korbanos at one stage and he hasn't brought the
other קרבן korban yet. הכל הולך אחר חטאת דברי רבי שמעון. hakol
holeich achar chatas divrei Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's
fixed by the חטאת. chatas. רבי יהודה אומר הכל הולך אחר אשם,
Rabbi Yehudah omer hakol holeich achar asham, it all goes by the
אשם. asham. רבי אליעזר אומר הכל הולך אחר צפורין, Rabbi Eliezer omer
hakol holeich achar tziporim, it all goes by the birds which goes
a week before. And basically the גמרא learns it says they all
learn it out from one פסוק pasuk that emphasizes that it says
the פסוק, pasuk, let me just check רש"י Rashi says it's something
what the פסוק, pasuk, it says אשר
לא תשיג ידו בטהרתו. asher lo sasig yado betaharato. So בטהרתו betaharato
his טהרה taharah process. So what does טהרה taharah process begin? With
the birds. Others says the טהרה taharah process ends with the אשם,
asham, that's where you use the blood of the אשם asham to
do the whole, you know, applying the blood of the אשם asham
and so. The other says טהרתו taharato here means becoming atoned, like
more metaphorical, and it means בחטאת. bachatas. So you have all three
opinions, which is the stage that establishes. He says look, if you're
taking the opinion of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehudah. It's too late. You
already brought your אשם asham *asham*. You can't do this trick. And
if it's like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon? *Rabbi Shimon* there's no problem
having done it out of order. Right. And if it's like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* that says that the חטאת chatat *chatas*
is when it's determined, so you can still do this trick. So
דאמר חטאת chatat, קבע *d'amar chatas kova* אף אגב דלא קריב אשם
asham *af agav de-lo kareiv asham*, although you didn't bring an אשם
asham, *asham*, so then there was no question to begin with. There's
a much easier answer according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*.
What's the easier answer according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*?
So remember, the question was how are you going to bring this
your קרבנות *korbanos* if you have a doubtful status? And assuming you
can't bring them a normal חטאת chatat *chatas*, a normal אשם asham,
*asham* based on doubt. So the answer was make yourself poor which
allow it to become a bird חטאת chatat. *chatas* which you'll bring
on doubt. So he says okay look that works according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* that says you can change your status
until you bring your חטאת *chatas*. But remember we said what about
the אשם asham *asham* and you said oh the אשם asham, *asham*
you brought a while ago. According to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi
Shimon* you don't have to say the אשם asham. *asham* you brought
a while ago because רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* actually says that you
can bring an אשם asham *asham* on doubt, okay, if you don't
know you're obligated you can do a whole stipulation. What's your stipulation?
Let's take a look.
So if it's רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* that says you can do
this trick then you didn't have to tell me you brought your
אשם asham. *asham* early. So אף אגב דלא קריב אשם asham נסי
אחרי *af agav de-lo kareiv asham nasei acharei*, even if you didn't
bring your אשם asham? *asham* you could bring another one. דהא שמעינן
ליה לרבי שמעון *de-ha shamin lay l'Rabbi Shimon* who says מייתי
ומתני *meivi v'masni* that if you don't know if you have to
bring an אשם *asham*, you can bring it and stipulate. Why? דתניא
*de-tanya*. אמר רבי שמעון למחר מייתי אשמו *amar Rabbi Shimon l'machar meivi
ashamo*. If this guy doesn't know whether he's obligated to bring an
אשם *asham* or not, whatever the whole discussion about he doesn't what
the exact scenario is doesn't bother us for now, anyway what does
somebody do who doesn't know if he has to bring his אשם
מצורע *asham mitzora*? He brings his אשם *asham* with his לוג *log*,
right, you have the לוג *log* of the oil which was used
in the process, עמו *imo*, ומעמידו בשער ניקנור
*v'maamido b'shaar nikanor*, you stand in the gate of Nicanor which is
the opening of the עזרה *azara* ומתני עליו *v'masni alav* and you
stipulate. The ברייתא *braisa* says ומעמידו בשער ניקנור *maamido b'shaar nikanor*, he's
not allowed to actually walk into the עזרה *azara* because he's a
מצורע *mitzora*. He's right at the opening and he stipulates. He says
ואומר *v'omer* אם מצורע הוא *im mitzora hu*, he says I'll put
it in the first person, if I'm a מצורע *mitzora* and I
have to bring this קרבן korban *korban* הרי אשם זה ולוגו עמו
*harei asham zeh v'logo imo*, whoops, I've brought my אשם *asham* with
the לוג *log*. ואם לאו *v'im lav*, and if I'm not a
מצורע *mitzora*, אשם זה יהא שלמים shelamim, נדבה *asham zeh yehei shelamim
nedavah*, let it just be a שלמים shelamim, *shelamim*. Now you can
do that because a שלמים *shelamim* by the way could be male
or female. So you could say if this isn't an אשם *asham*
let it be a שלמים *shelamim*. But why can't you say the
same by a חטאת *chatas*? If it isn't a חטאת *chatas* let
it be a שלמים *shelamim*. So you could except that a חטאת
*chatas* you put the blood at the corners at the top of
the מזבח *mizbeach* and a שלמים *shelamim* you put it at the
bottom on the on the corners on the edges of the מזבח
*mizbeach*. So the point is with an אשם *asham*, a חטאת *chatas*
you can't say either way I've got my bases covered. But with
an אשם *asham* you can. It could either be an אשם *asham*
or שלמים *shelamim*, they could both be male and I'm doing the
blood in the same place. So I'll just say whichever it is,
if it has to be an אשם *asham* it's an אשם *asham*.
If it's not an אשם *asham* it'll be a שלמים *shelamim* and
stipulate. ואותו אשם *v'oso asham*, so what do you do with that
אשם *asham*? You have to treat it as both an אשם *asham*
and שלמים *shelamim* and have all of the requirements. So what you
have to do for it is שוחטו בצפון *shochato batzafon*, you have
to shecht it in the north of the of the מזבח *mizbeach*
because that it has as if it were an אשם *asham*. As
a שלמים *shelamim* it could be anywhere, as an אשם *asham* it
has to be in the north קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim*. וטעון מתנות
בהונות *v'tan matanos bahonos*, you have to put the blood on the
on the you know the thumbs and the toes or whatever of
the מצורע *mitzora* because that's what you're doing with it is using
it דמטהר *de-mitaher* the מצורע *mitzora*. וטעון סמיכה *v'tei'un semichah*, now you
would do סמיכה *semichah* on it. Now רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that's
only because it's a שלמים *shelamim*. An אשם *asham* you do not
do סמיכה *semichah*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says no you do סמיכה *semichah*
in an אשם *asham*, but there's a question if you do סמיכה
*semichah* on the אשם *asham* of a מצורע *mitzora*. So anyway we're
emphasizing here that there's definitely סמיכה *semichah*. One minute. Why would be
a question
if you do סמיכה *semichah* on אשם *asham* of מצורע *mitzora*? Because
take a look based on whatever תוספות Tosafot בסמיכה *Tosfos b'semichah*, you
can look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*. ונסכים *v'nesachim*, and you bring נסכים
*nesachim* because
okay now נסכים *nesachim* actually you would anyway bring regardless but תוספות
Tosafot's *Tosfos* says
one minute.
Right. So anyway so it's actually interesting because again normally the normal
אשם *asham* does not require נסכים *nesachim* only if a שלמים *shelamim*
does. But here the אשם מצורע *asham mitzora* does require נסכים *nesachim*.
So תוספות *Tosfos* actually says it really doesn't matter what this is,
אשם מצורע *asham mitzora* or שלמים *shelamim*, either way requires נסכים *nesachim*.
But nevertheless we're pointing it out because normal אשמות *ashamos* would not
get נסכים *nesachim*. So anyway here you're going to bring נסכים *nesachim*
and ותנופת חזה ושוק *tnufat chazeh v'shok* you would wave the breast
and the thighs. That's something you specifically do with it if it's
a שלמים *shelamim*. Okay so basically you don't know if it's a
שלמים *shelamim* or it's an אשם *asham*. So you treat it as
an אשם *asham*, you שוחט *shocheit* it in the north, you do
the whole process with the ears and the toe and the thumb.
That's the whole way he becomes טהור *tahor* but you also treat
it as a possible שלמים *shelamim* and you do the waving of
the breast and the thigh and so on. Now who eats it?
If it's a שלמים *shelamim* the owners can eat it. If it's
an אשם *asham* only the male כהנים *kohanim*. So again you have
to be strict because it might be an אשם *asham*. ונאכל לזכרי
כהונה ליום ולילה *v'ne'echal l'zichrei kehunah l'yom valailah*. Okay only for male
כהנים *kohanim* and only for one day as an אשם *asham*. So
anyway that's what רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says. רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*
says I don't know what you're I mean you crazy about the
אשם *asham* you can just stipulate. You can't do it by חטאת
*chatas* but you can do it. So he says like this if
it's רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* who you can still play this trick.
game and give away your property and become a and bring a
חטאת העוף, why did you have to say you brought your אשם
before? He'll let you bring your אשם now. Okay, but anyway ולא
הודו לו חכמים לרבי שמעון. v'lo hodu lo chachamim l'Rabbi Shimon. And
by the way, why would anybody argue on רבי שמעון? But no,
there are חכמים chachamim who argue on רבי שמעון מפני שמביא קדשים
לבית הפסול. mipnei shemeivi kodashim l'veit hapsul. Such a perfect answer, but
the reason they don't like it is that maybe it's a שלמים,
and if it's a שלמים, you have a lot of people that
can eat it and you can eat it for two days, and
now you're treating it as an אשם, and only male כהנים can
eat it and only for one day. So you might have to...
it might lead to it having to be burnt and destroyed before
its time, and you don't want to do that. It was such
a perfect answer, they didn't like it because of that concern. But
anyway, he's saying look, according to רבי שמעון, you're right, you could
say make yourself poor, but then you wouldn't... but the אשם, you
could have just said play this... do this trick, why would you
have had to say the אשם was already brought? So the גמרא
answers and says שמואל סבר לה כרבי שמעון בחדא ופליג עליה בחדא.
Shmuel savar lah k'Rabbi Shimon b'chada u'plig leh b'chada. You're right, according
to רבי שמעון, it would have been a nice simple answer, make
yourself poor, bring the חטאת as a poor, and as far as
the אשם, you could anyway do this trick. But שמואל Shmuel was
bothered because he didn't rule like רבי שמעון about being able to
stipulate about an אשם. So he figured out how to get you
out of a חטאת, you make yourself poor, not get you out,
but let you bring the bird חטאת which you can bring out
of doubt, but אשם wasn't the solution, so he didn't hold like
רבי שמעון for that, so he had to say you had already
brought your אשם. Yes, Charlie.
This is a very strange technical question to be coming from Alexandria.
Yes, well that was the point I made. It's bizarre that these
are the three questions that come from Alexandria. So, I don't know
how to explain that. Anyway, let's go on. I actually didn't understand
the whole issue about the אשם anyway because, whatever, I had a...
I thought like why didn't we just say that first he made
himself poor and then he brought his אשם? Meaning maybe the קרבן
that got mixed up was the חטאת. Anyway, I thought there was
another answer. Anyway, moving on, the גמרא says like this, שלשה דברי
אגדה. shlosha divrei agada. Moving on to something a little bit lighter
for once. Three areas of אגדה. Here's the questions they asked. כתוב
אחד אומר, katuv echad omer, one פסוק pasuk says כי לא אחפוץ
במות המת, ki lo achpotz b'mot hamet, that
says I do not desire the death of the dead person, whatever
I don't desire that a sinner should die is a paraphrase. וכתוב
אחד אומר, v'katuv echad omer, another פסוק pasuk says כי חפץ השם
להמיתם, ki chafetz Hashem lahamitam,
God wanted to kill them, the sinners. So what is it? Does
God want the sinners to die or not? כאן בעושים תשובה כאן
בשאינם עושים תשובה. kan b'osim teshuvah kan b'she'einam osim teshuvah. Okay, if
you do תשובה, teshuvah, then God won't want you to die even
if you're a sinner, but if you don't do תשובה, teshuvah, which
is pretty harsh, whatever happened to you know who was it who
said you know pray that יתמו חטאים ולא חוטאים, yitmu chata'im v'lo
chot'im, ברוריה, Beruriah, anyway, okay. Anyway, maybe God anyway should want them
to die because he wants to give them time to do תשובה.
teshuvah. Maybe I would prefer to read it that way. עושים osim
תשובה teshuvah more not that they have done תשובה teshuvah but that
there's the anticipation or the hope that they'll do תשובה. teshuvah. Only
when it's completely for sure clear that they're not going to, anyway
I don't know, but I think עושים osim is not that they
have done, but you know maybe it's more God will want, God
always gives us, I mean it's what we say on ראש השנה
ויום כיפור, Rosh Hashanah v'Yom Kippur, you know, כי לא, ki lo,
you know, because you don't want, you want people to live and
you want to give people a chance to do תשובה. teshuvah. כתוב
אחד אומר, katuv echad omer, one פסוק pasuk says כי לא ישא
פנים ולא יקח שוחד, ki lo yisa fanim v'lo yikach shochad, God
does not show favor and take bribes. וכתוב אחד אומר, v'katuv echad
omer, another פסוק pasuk says ישא השם פניו אליך, yisa Hashem panav
elecha,
God shall lift up His countenance to you. תוספות points out that
this is not really a problem because this is not saying that
God shows favor. It's not God is lifting up your face which
is the idiom for showing favor. It's saying God is lifting up
His face towards you, meaning it's not He's showing favoritism towards you,
He's just being nice, you know, to you. So it's really תוספות
points out that even that there are other פסוקים pesukim you could
have quoted that would have been more problematic. This in פשט pshat
is not even such a problem. But the answer is כאן קודם
גזר דין כאן לאחר גזר דין, kan kodem gzar din kan l'achar
gzar din, that before the judgment has been sealed then God will
maybe, you know, waive certain things, show leniency and so on. After
the judgment has been sealed, then there
is then you're going to get the strict judgment. Now of course
the interesting question is how does that idea of גזר דין gzar
din fit with the previous idea of תשובה? teshuvah? Right?
How about תשובה? teshuvah? Does תשובה teshuvah work after גזר דין? gzar
din? And if תשובה teshuvah works after גזר דין gzar din then
maybe השם Hashem is נושא פנים. nosei fanim. Or we're supposed to
assume that תשובה teshuvah doesn't work after גזר דין. gzar din. So
תוספות plays out some of those questions based on other גמרות. gemarot.
If we get, let's finish the דף, daf, if we get a
time I'll go back and discuss some of תוספות's discussion. Okay so
then it says like this, כתוב אחד אומר, katuv echad omer, כי
בחר השם בציון, ki bachar Hashem b'Tzion, God has chosen in Zion.
This is actually very relevant for תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, you sitting
you might have learned this גמרא yesterday. וכתוב אחד אומר, v'katuv echad
omer, כי על אפי ועל חמתי היתה לי העיר הזאת מן היום
אשר בנו אותה עד היום הזה, ki al api v'al chamati hayta
li ha'ir hazot min hayom asher banu otah ad hayom hazeh, because
my anger and you know was directed against this city from the
day they had built it until this day to destroy it. This
is in ירמיהו. Yirmeyahu. So God had always been planning to destroy
the city from the very day it was built. What does that
mean? How are we supposed to understand that He chose Jerusalem if
He had always been planning to destroy it? So the גמרא says
אוי. oy. גמרא says כאן קודם שנשא שלמה את בת פרעה כאן
לאחר שנשא שלמה את בת פרעה. kan kodem shensah Shlomo et bat
Paroh kan l'achar shensah Shlomo et bat Paroh. This is pretty heavy.
So there was a moment when it was chosen in the time
of דוד ושלמה. David u'Shlomo. But then, when it was clear that
the whole sort of, you know, Jewish Commonwealth was going downhill when
he married בת פרעה bat Paroh and maybe that was the sign,
I'm interpreting this not as just Shlomo's personal sin, but the sign
that we were not going to remain a, you know, you know,
sort of with the religious standard, the moral standards that we should
have been having. And so it was the first sign for the
fall of the, you know, that we were going downhill. So that's
pretty heavy. But the, you know, the פסוק pasuk is itself pretty
heavy that God had been planning from the day it was built.
So, yes. How does that answer from the day it's built? Oh,
not exactly. The time that it was built. Roughly around the time
he married בת פרעה bat Paroh on the day that the Temple
was dedicated. So he chose it before, but starting at the day
that it was built. Yeah. Alright. Either way, it's still close enough
in the general time frame. Alright. Pretty heavy, pretty heavy. I mean,
you've got very serious questions, actually. I mean, you know, because if
you I will actually say the following, and this actually does fit
a little bit more with Alexandria, you know, I mean, Philo was
from Alexandria was much more like philosophically oriented. If you take it
away from the פסוקים, psukim, these are, I think, important philosophical questions.
The first question is, look, you know, how do we deal with
the idea of destruction of the Temple and at the same time
believe that, you know, that this was chosen and, you know, that
it was the that it was God's house and it was the
chosen place and where the chosen people, and you know, how do
we deal with the sense of destruction that fits in? How does
that fit into all of that? You know, the other question also
that like, you know, מידת הדין midat hadin versus מידת הרחמים, midat
harachamim, is God, you know, does God show compassion? Does he not?
You know, in what way is he a just God and in
what way does he,
you know, does he bend that justice for the sake of compassion?
So I mean some of these questions are not just contradictions in
פסוקים, psukim, right? I mean you could have said, okay, the פסוק
pasuk in ירמיהו Yirmiyahu was an exaggeration, it doesn't mean God was
really planning to destroy it from the first day. But I think
that there's still like some profound philosophical questions here, right? How do
you fit in the idea of destruction with the idea of suffering
and you know with the idea of chosenness which is part which
is I think very relevant to the Tisha B'Av. Alright, so now
we get to a little more fun point. שלשה דברי בורות. shlosha
divrei borut. Three foolish questions. אשתו של לוט מהו שתטמא? ishto she-Lot
mahu she-titameh? Does the pillar of salt that was Lot's wife, does
that cause טומאת מת? tumat met? Why is that a foolish question?
Well, he thought it was foolish. I mean if a dead person
can, right? Well, that person causes טומאה anyway. We were just giving
extra טומאה. So maybe you're right. I don't know.
Could you use her for your challah? Mark, you know, you know
what the you know some people say there's no such thing as
foolish questions, right? But here he thought there was such a thing.
He felt, you know, that already was foolish. אמר להם מת מטמא
ואין נציב מלח מטמא. amar lahem met metameh ve-ein netsiv melach metameh.
Of course, it causes טומאה, not a pile of salt, which is,
you know, it seems like it's so foolish, but of course the
question does become at what stage has something so transformed that it's
no longer considered the original thing? Okay. בן השונמית, ben HaShunamit, the
son of the Shunamite that was brought back to life, right? מהו
שיטמא? mahu she-itameh? Does he cause טומאה? Maybe he's a living walking
corpse. He's a zombie. He's a you think it's a good question,
right? So he's a zombie. אמר להם מת מטמא ואין חי מטמא.
amar lahem met metameh ve-ein chai metameh. I'm sorry, he's he's no
longer dead, he's now alive. Now of course, yes. Well, this is
actually more complicated than that because the people in the room when
he was dead would have had טומאת אוהל. tumat ohel. Yes. So,
ah, so one of the מפרשים mefarshim says that maybe actually he's
not a מת, but maybe he himself is טמא for having been
in the same room he himself was as a dead person. Alright.
Anyway,
but there actually is an interesting question about this, about the whole
concept of like תחיית המתים techiyat hametim comes up in medical ethics
also, that if you is it possible to say that somebody is
clinically dead and then there would but but you could if you
have or halachically dead, but it's possible to resuscitate them. And do
you have then a מצוה mitzvah to essentially be like מחיה מתים,
mechiyeh metim, as it were? הצלה Hatzalah does that. In other words,
they will not leave a person to die if they think there
is any possibility. Oh that I understand. But let's say you define
dead as actually even so, they'll still continue to have them. Right,
but the question is, is that because you're saying halachically it's not
death as long as there's a chance to resuscitate? Which is the
easier thing to say. Or do you say halachically they're dead but
you still have a מצוה mitzvah of פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh or
whatever, even on a dead person if you can bring them back
into life? פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh to do תחיית המתים. techiyat hametim.
Anyway. You shouldn't be allowed to do תחיית המתים. techiyat hametim.
Because that's what do you mean it's ואהבת לרעך כמוך? ve-ahavta l'reiacha
kamocha?
Okay, so now it says,
anyway, מתים
לעתיד לבוא, metim le-atid lavo, all of these as you see are
around the same issue. מתים לעתיד לבוא צריכים הזאה שלישי ושביעי או
אין צריכים? metim le-atid lavo tsrichim haza'ah shelishi ve-shvi'i o ein tsrichim?
When they come back to dead, right, sort of like the בן
השונמית, ben HaShunamit, they've been dead. So this is just like, they
were טמא from themselves. Do they need to be ashes of, you
know, of to do the sprinkling of the ashes
to become טהור? אמר להם לכשיחיו נחכם להם. amar lahem likshe-yichyu ne-chakem
lahem. And where when they come alive then then we'll worry about
it then. Same
thing. But the other one, the other one already happened. Here it
says, you know, any questions about תחיית המתים Techiat HaMeitim we'll worry
about when it happens. So he says איכא דאמרי, ika d'amrei, some
say he says לכשיבא משה רבינו עמהם. liksheyavo Moshe Rabbeinu imahem. Oh,
when that happens Moshe will be brought back to life as well,
we can ask him, he'll probably have a good answer to that.
Very sarcastic. Yes, that's definitely sarcastic. And Rabbi Yehoshua was one of
the more rational תנאים. It's interesting that he's the one that... Well
but still, I mean, you understand not wanting to get into questions
about תחיית המתים. Techiat HaMeitim. But anyway. Yeah, but it is interesting,
I agree with Rachel, like why is it considered so, you know,
why are we just immediately labeling it as דברי בורות? divrei borot?
Anyway, I just want to see something. Are you trying to stump
them?
Right. They're playing stump the rabbi. Okay anyway, moving on. So let's
just finish up the last three.
שלושה דברי דרך ארץ. Shelosha divrei derech eretz. מה יעשה אדם ויחכם?
Mah ya'aseh adam veyichkam? What should a person do if they want
to get smart?
אמר להם, Amar lahem, ירבה בישיבה וימעיט בסחורה. Yirbeh b'yeshiva v'yam'it b'sechorah.
Spend a lot of time sitting and learning and don't spend time
running around trying to make money. אמרו, amru, so they said to
him, הרבה עשו כן ולא הועיל להם. Harbeh asu chen v'lo ho'il
lahem. A lot of people tried that and it didn't succeed.
Okay, yes. אלא, ela, יבקשו רחמים ממי שהחכמה שלו. Yivakshu rachamim mimi
shehachochmah shelo.
It's not clear if they're saying this or he's saying this back.
Anyway, but so rather you have to pray to God. שנאמר, Shene'emar,
כי ה' יתן חכמה. ki Hashem yiten chochmah. God gives wisdom. מפיו
דעת ותבונה, Mipiv da'at utvunah, from His mouth is understanding and knowledge.
So תני רבי חייא, Tani Rabbi Chiyya, משל למלך בשר ודם Mashal
lemelech basar vadam שעשה סעודה לעבדיו, she'asah se'udah l'avadav, a story like
a king who made a feast for his servants. ומשגר לאוהביו ממה
שלפניו. Umeshager l'ohavav mimah shelefanav. So he sends his students to what
gift does he send, he sends them the food from what's in
front of him. So God has, God has the wisdom, if you're
beloved of God he'll send you a gift. So anyway, I don't
exactly get what the משל mashal helps more than the פסוק. pasuk.
But anyway, מאי קמשמע לן? Mai kamashma lan? Now if we're saying
that the idea is that you have to pray, so why is
he saying you should sit and learn? דהא בלא הא לא סגי,
Deha be'lo ha lo sagi, because it doesn't help to pray if
you're not sitting and learning. Okay, it's like the old story, right,
the guy goes, you know, he opens up the ארון aron and
he's like this, you know, older Jew, he's been, you know, and
he always had hard times and he says רבונו של עולם, Ribbono
Shel Olam, my life I've been doing everything You wanted and I
did all the מצוות, mitzvot, I spent all my time learning תורה,
he says never never have I like won a lottery, why why?
So a voice comes out and says
idiot, buy a ticket!
So anyway, so you have to learn. Now I do wonder by
the way if the point of this little משל mashal of sending
to those that love him and so on is to tell you
that maybe even the sitting of learning what it does besides the
obvious this-worldly thing of helping to make you smart is it also
shows God demonstrates that the value that this has and so on
and makes you the person worthy of the God's gift of wisdom.
So you know maybe that's also part of what's going on here.
Not like you do your part God does His part, but also
that makes you the אוהב ohev here that's worthy of this blessing.
So מה יעשה אדם ויתעשר? Mah ya'aseh adam veyit'asher? Now how about
a person doesn't want to get, doesn't want to get wise, they
want to get rich, what should they do? אמר להם, Amar lahem,
he said to them, ירבה בסחורה. Yirbeh b'sechorah. So okay go and
do, you know, spend a lot of time in business. וישא ויתן
באמונה. Veyisa veyiten be'emunah. Ah, but also have
honesty, right, your business dealings should all be with integrity. אמרו לו,
Amru lo, הרבה עשו כן ולא הועיל לו. Harbeh asu chen v'lo
ho'il lo. Many did that and it didn't succeed.
אלא, again question who's responding to אלא, יבקש רחמים ממי שהעושר שלו.
Yivakesh rachamim mimi sheha'osher shelo. They should ask for compassion from the
one who has all the wealth. שנאמר, Shene'emar, לי הכסף ולי הזהב,
Li hakesef v'li hazahav, to Me is the gold and silver. מאי
קמשמע לן? Mai kamashma lan? So then what is, you know, the
point about saying these other things if it's about prayer? דהא בלא
הא לא סגי, Deha be'lo ha lo sagi, you can't have one
without the other. You need to do your part, God will do
His part. Interestingly, this ירבה בסחורה, yirbeh b'sechorah, if you look, the
הגר"א ha'Gra cuts it out. Why? Because if you're ירבה בסחורה yirbeh
b'sechorah you're being ימעיט בישיבה yam'it b'yeshiva and you know especially הגר"א
ha'Gra whatever was very much about you know totally prioritizing תלמוד תורה.
talmud Torah. So he would like to I think see that you
could both spend a lot of time learning and make money as
long as you're וישא ויתן באמונה, yisa veyiten be'emunah, you don't have
to ירבה בסחורה. yirbeh b'sechorah. Okay, but our text certainly is there's
a certain tradeoff about which you're going to do. He amended the...
Well, there's always a question when people have those different versions whether
they're actually reflecting different manuscripts or what they're intuiting is the right
text or... Because how can a person argue on the משנה? Right,
so no, question is that he's claiming that that is the actual
text. Is he doing it based on a manuscript? Based on his
intuition of what the text should be? Not clear. מה יעשה אדם
ויהיו לו בנים זכרים? Mah ya'aseh adam veyihyu lo banim zacharim? What
should a person do to have male children? Which was of course
what everybody wanted. אמר להם, Amar lahem, ישא אשה ההוגנת לו, Yisa
ishah hahogenet lo, marry a woman fitting for you. Oh, what? We
had it. We had it before. ויקדש עצמו בשעת תשמיש. Veyikadesh atzmo
b'sha'at tashmish. And should sanctify yourself at the moment of sex, meaning,
pressing exactly what that means. רש"י says לשמש בצניעות, leshammesh bitzni'ut, a
certain degree of modesty. How exactly that translates and how that fits
into other statements... about the
גמרא about the sex between husband and wife is a larger discussion,
but anyway, אמרו, they said to him, הרבה עשו כן ולא הועילו,
harbe asu ken v'lo ho'ilu, many tried it, it didn't work. אלא
יבקש רחמים ממי שהבנים שלו. ela yivakesh rachamim mimi shehabanim shelo. Again,
same answer. Ask from the one who has the ability to give
sons, שנאמר: shene'emar: הנה נחלת ה' בנים שכר פרי הבטן. hinei nachalat
Hashem banim s'char pri habaten. The
inheritance of God is sons, the reward of the fruit of the
womb. So מאי קמשמע לן? mai kamashma lan? דהא בלא הא לא
סגי. d'ha b'la ha lo sagi. You need to do both. Now
the גמרא, however, ends up with a דרשה derasha which takes it
in a different direction. Now we say תפילה, tefillah, יקדש עצמו בשעת
תשמיש, yikadesh atzmo b'sha'at tashmish, here's a different answer. מאי שכר פרי
הבטן? mai s'char pri habaten? אמר רבי חמא ברבי חנינא, amar Rabi
Chama b'rebi Chanina, בשכר שמשהין עצמן בבטן כדי שתזריע אשתו תחילה. bis'char
shemash'hin atzman babeten kedei shetazria ishto techilah.
We had this before, with the reward that the husbands wait, sort
of, hold themselves back in the act of sex in order that
the woman should give forth seed first, should first have pleasure and
orgasm before the man. So the fact of that, נותן לו הקדוש
ברוך הוא שכר פרי הבטן. noten lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu s'char pri
habaten. That's the way you get male children, by making sure that
your wife is satisfied during the act of sex. We'll end with
that. Thank you people, bye.